<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>True report of the gainefull, prosperous and speedy voiage to Iaua in the East Indies, performed by a fleete of eight ships of Amsterdam which set forth from Texell in Holland, the first of Maie 1598, Stilo Nouo, whereof foure returned againe the 19. of Iuly anno 1599. in lesse than 15. moneths, the other foure went forward from Iaua for the Moluccas.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04364</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1251</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22045308</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22045308</idno>
            <idno type="VID">24997</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04364)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 24997)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1728:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>True report of the gainefull, prosperous and speedy voiage to Iaua in the East Indies, performed by a fleete of eight ships of Amsterdam which set forth from Texell in Holland, the first of Maie 1598, Stilo Nouo, whereof foure returned againe the 19. of Iuly anno 1599. in lesse than 15. moneths, the other foure went forward from Iaua for the Moluccas.</title>
                  <author>Neck, Jacob Cornelissoon van, ca. 1564-1638.</author>
                  <author>Warwyck, Wijbrant van, ca. 1569-1615.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by P.S. for W. Aspley, and are to be sold at the signe of the Tygers head in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1599?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.) and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D².</note>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 10 misnumbered 9.</note>
                  <note>The expedition set out under the command of Jacob van Neck and Wijbrant van Warwyck.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>East Indies --  Description and travel.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Commerce --  History --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:24997:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24997:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24997:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24997:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24997:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:24997:3"/>
A TRVE REPORT of the gainefull, proſperous and <hi>ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy voiage to Iaua in the Eaſt Indies,</hi> performed by a fleete of eight <hi>ſhips of Amſterdam:</hi> WHICH SET FORTH FROM Texell in Holland, the firſt of Maie <hi>1598. Stilo Nouo. Whereof foure returned againe the</hi> 19. of Iuly Anno 1599. in leſſe then 15. moneths, the other foure went forward from Iaua for the Moluccas.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>ET VSQVE AD NVBES VERITAS TVA</head>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by P. S. for W. Aſpley, and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Tygers head in Paules Church-yard.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:24997:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:24997:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> True report of the gainfull, proſperous, and <hi>ſpeedy voiage to Iaua in the Eaſt Indies, performed</hi> by a fleet of 8. ſhips of Amſterdam: which ſet forth from <hi>Texell in Holland the firſt of Maie 1598. Stilo Nouo.</hi> Whereof foure returned againe the 19. of Iuly Anno 1599. in leſſe then 15. moneths: the other foure went forward from Iaua for the Moluccas.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREAS in the yeare of our Lord 1595. a certaine company of ſubſtantial merchants of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam in Holland did build and ſet forth for the Eaſt Indies four well appointed ſhippes, whereof three came home An. 1597. with ſmall profit (as already in ſundry languages is declared) Yet neuertheleſſe the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid company, in hope of better ſucceſſe, made out the laſt yeare 1598. for a ſecond voiage, a fleete of eight gallant ſhips, to wit, The ſhippe called the Mauritius, lately returned from that former voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, <note place="margin">1. Mauritius.</note> being of burden two hundreth and thirty laſt, or foure hundreth and ſixty tunnes, or thereabouts. This ſhippe was Admirall of the fleete. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter wherof was <hi>Godevart Iohnſon,</hi> the Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie or Factor <hi>Cornelius Heemskerck,</hi> and the Pilot <hi>Kees Collen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:24997:5"/>
The ſecond ſhip called the Amſterdam, was of the <note place="margin">2. Amſterdam.</note> burden of four hundreth &amp; ſixty tuns. The maſters name was <hi>Claes Iohnſon Melcknap;</hi> The Factor or commiſſarie <hi>Iacob Heemskerck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third was named Hollandia, about the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <note place="margin">3. Hollandia.</note> of ſixe hundreth tuns: which had likewiſe been in the former voiage. The Maſter was <hi>Symon Lambertſon</hi> or <hi>Mawe,</hi> the Factor Maſt. <hi>Witte Nijn,</hi> who died in the voyage before Bantam, and in his roome ſucceeded <hi>Iohn Iohnſon ſmith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The name of the fourth ſhip was Gelderland, of <note place="margin">4. Gelderland.</note> burden about foure hundreth tuns. Maſter wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was <hi>Iohn Browne,</hi> Factor or commiſſarie <hi>Hans Hendrickſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fift was called Zeelandia, of the burden of <note place="margin">5. Zeelandia.</note> three hundreth &amp; ſixtie tuns. The maſter was <hi>Iohn Corneliſon,</hi> the Commiſſary or Factor <hi>N. Brewer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſixt ſhip named Vtrecht of the burden of <note place="margin">6. Vtrecht.</note> two hundreth &amp; ſixtie tuns. The Maſter was <hi>Iohn Martſen,</hi> the Factor or commiſſary <hi>Adrian Veen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeuenth, a pinnas called Friſland, of burden <note place="margin">7. Friſland.</note> about ſeuenty tuns. The Maſter <hi>Iacob Corneliſon.</hi> The Factor <hi>Walter Willekens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eighth, a pinnas that had been in the former <note place="margin">8. Oueriſſell.</note> voiage, called the Pidgeon, now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Oueriiſſel, of the burden of fifty tuns. The Maſter <hi>Symon Iohnſon.</hi> The Factor <hi>Arent Hermanſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this fleete was Generall and Admirall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Iacob Neck:</hi> Viceadmirall <hi>Wybrand van War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick:</hi> and Rereadmirall <hi>Iacob Heemskerck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With this fleet of eight ſhips we made ſaile from Texell the firſt of May 1598. <hi>Stilo Nouo,</hi> being the 21. of Aprill, after the account of England, and ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with good ſpeed vnto the <hi>Cabo de bona ſperanza:</hi> as further ſhal appeare by a Iournal annexed vnto the end of this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:24997:5"/>
Being paſt the Cape, the 7. and 8. of Auguſt, by a ſtonne of weather fiue ſhips were ſeparated from the Admirall, who afterwardes came together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine before Bantam.</p>
            <p>The 26. of Auguſt with three ſhippes wee came within the view of Madagaſcar, and the 29 wee <note place="margin">They meete with a ſhip of Zeland.</note> met with a ſhip of Zeeland called the Long-barke, which had put to ſea before vs, and now kept aloofe from vs, ſuppoſing we were enemies: but at length perceiuing by our flagges what we were, they ſent their Pinnas aboord vs, reioycing greatly to haue met with vs, becauſe that diuers of their men were ſicke, and ten were already dead: and they had in all but ſeuen men aboord the ſhippe that were meat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whole, and eleuen marriners to guide the ſhippe. Wee agreed to relieue them with ſome ſupplie of men: but through darkeneſſe and great winde wee loſt them againe.</p>
            <p>After this, we the Admiral Mauritius, the Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landia, &amp; the pinnas Oueriiſſell keeping together, came to the Iſland of Santa Maria, before the <note place="margin">The Iſle of Santa Maria.</note> great bay of Antogil in Madagaſcar: where wee got a ſmall quantity of Rice. We tooke the King priſoner, who paide for his Ranſome a Cow and a fat calfe.</p>
            <p>In this Iſland we found no great commodity: for being the month of September, the ſeaſon was not for any fruits: the Oranges had but flowers: Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons were ſcant: of Sugar-canes and Hens there was ſome ſtore, but the Inhabitants were not very forward in bringing them out.</p>
            <p>Heere wee ſawe the hunting of the Whale (a ſtrange paſtime) certaine Indians in a Canoa, or <note place="margin">Killing of the Whale.</note> boate following a great Whale, and with a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Iron, which they caſt forth, piercing the whals body, which yron was faſtned to a long rope made of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:24997:6"/>
the barkes of trees, and ſo tied faſt to their Canoa. All this while pricking and wounding the Whale ſo much as they could, they made him furiouſly to ſtriue too and fro, ſwiftly ſwimming in the ſea, pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the canoa after him: ſometimes toſſing it vp and downe, as lightly as if it had been a ſtrawe: the Indians in the meane time being cunning ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers taking ſmall care though they were caſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord, tooke faſt hold by the boat ſtil, and ſo after ſome continuance of this ſport the whale wearied &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xing faint, and ſtaining the ſea red with his bloud, they haled him toward the ſhore, and when they had gotten him ſo neare ſhore on the ſhallowe that the moſt part of him appeared aboue water, they drew him aland and he wed him in pieces, euery one ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereof what pleaſed them, which was to vs a ſtrange ſight. It is reported that the Indians of Terra Florida vſe the like fiſhing for the Whale. Our men might haue taken ſome part thereof, but refuſed it: the pieces therof were ſo like larde or fat bacon.</p>
            <p>From thence we made toward the great Bay of <note place="margin">The Bay of Antogill.</note> Antogill and ancored vnder the Iſland, where wee tooke in freſh water.</p>
            <p>Our Indians that were brought from thence by them of the former voiage (the names of whome were <hi>Madagaſcar</hi> the one, and the other <hi>Laurence)</hi> wee offered to ſet there on land, but they refuſed, chuſing rather to tarry with vs and to be apparel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, then to go naked in their owne countrey: wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and moyling for a miſerable liuing, oppoſing their bare ſkins to the vehemency of the ſunne and weather: and their excuſe was, that in that place they were ſtrangers and had none acquaintance. <note place="margin">How long their beere continued good.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Our beere continued good vntill we were paſſed the <hi>Cape de bona ſperanza.</hi> From thence we began to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:24997:6"/>
mingle it with water hauing a portion of wine al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vs twiſe a day, and this allowance continued vntill our returne into Holland.</p>
            <p>We went with our boates vp the riuer ſeeking refreſhing: but the Inhabitants gaue vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by ſignes that wee might returne, for there was nothing to be had. Wee rowed into the riuer about three leagues, and found their report to bee true. The cauſe was, that the Kings made warre there one againſt an other, and ſo all the victuals were in manner deſtroied, inſomuch that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants themſelues many of them periſhed for hunger, and in one of theſe battailes one of their Kings was lately ſlaine. Wherfore after fiue daies abode and no longer, we departed, &amp; in Gods name made to ſea again, directing our courſe the ſixteenth of September for Iaua. About the ninteenth of Nouember we came within ſight of Sumatra, and the 26. of the ſame moneth 1598. wee in the three ſhippes aforeſaid, to wit, the Mauritius our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall, the Hollandia, and the Oueriſſell, arriued <note place="margin">They arriue at Bantam.</note> befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the citty of Bantam in Iaua. Preſently vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this our arriuall, our Admirall and Generall Maſter <hi>Iacob van Neck,</hi> ſought with all friendſhip to traffique with the people of the ſaide towne of Bantam, ſending Maſter <hi>Cornelis Heemskerck</hi> on land to ſhew them what we were, for they thought vs to be the very ſame men that had been there the yeare before, and al that while guarded the ſea-coſt, as being aſſuredly perſuaded that we were pirates and ſea rouers. But we, to make them vnderſtand the contrary, ſent on lande one <hi>Abdoll</hi> of China a captiue of theirs, whom we brought from them in our firſt voyage; by whoſe meanes we got audience <note place="margin">They preſent their letters and gifts.</note> and credite: and ſo we preſented our gifts and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to the King, which was but a childe: and the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:24997:7"/>
chiefe gouernour called <hi>Cephat,</hi> hauing the kingly authority, moſt thankfully receiued the ſame in the name of his King. The ſaid preſents were a faire couered cup of ſiluer and gilt, certaine veluets and clothes of ſilke, with very fine drinking glaſſes and excellent looking glaſſes, and ſuch other gifts more. Likewiſe we preſented our letters ſealed very coſtly with the great ſeale of the noble &amp; mighty lords the Eſtates generall of the vnited Prouinces, and of prince <hi>Mauritz,</hi> whome they termed their Prince. Which letters were by them receiued with great reuerence, creeping vpon their knees: and (the ſame being well peruſed, read, and examined) they found thereby our honeſt intent and determination for traffike: inſomuch that a mutuall league of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and alliance was concluded, and we were freely licenſed to trade and traffike in ſuch wiſe, that euen <note place="margin">Trade licenſed</note> the fourth day of our arriual we began to lade; and within foure or fiue weekes all our foure ſhips ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken in their full fraight, were ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part.</p>
            <p>When our three ſhippes aforeſaid had remained there welnigh a moneth, about Newyearſ-tide ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued the other fiue ſhippes of our company before mentioned in very good manner, and well conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And ſo our whole fleete of eight ſhips ioyfully <note place="margin">The whole fleet meet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Bantam.</note> met together, and had none or very fewe ſicke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons among them, hauing loſt by death in the whole fleete but 35 men in all, of which number ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed through their owne negligence. Vpon this happy meeting wee diſplaied our flags, ſtreamers, and enſignes after the braueſt manner, honouring and greeting one one another with volleies of ſhot, making good cheere, and (which was no ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) growing more deeply in fauour with the townſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Bantam. Vnto vs were daily brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:24997:7"/>
in Prauwes or Indian boats great quantity of hens, egs, Cocos, bonanes, ſugar-canes, cakes made of rice, and a certaine kinde of good drinke which is there made by the men of China. Thus the people daily bartered with vs for pewter and other wares, giuing ſo much virtuals for a pewter ſpoone, as might well ſuffice one man for an whole weeke. Wee trucked likewiſe for diuers other things, as for porcellan diſhes and ſuch like. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be it that which our Indian <hi>Abdoll</hi> declared (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that more ſhips were comming beſides the three aforeſaid, and that others beſide them alſo were ſent out of Zeland) little tended to our commodity: for thereupon the Iauans tooke occaſion to inhanſe <note place="margin">The price of pepperinhan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> the price of their pepper; inſomuch that we were forced to pay for 55 pounds of pepper firſt three, and afterward foure Reals of eight: neither did they demaund or call for any thing ſo much as for the ſaid Reals of eight. Mercery or haberdaſhers wares were in no ſuch requeſt as money. Alſo we much marueiled how the Iauans ſhould tell vs of more ſhippes to come, making ſignes with their foure fingers and thumb, that foure Lyma (which word in their language ſignifieth ſhippes) were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
            <p>And here you are to vnderſtand, that our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Maſter <hi>Van Neck,</hi> together with the commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries or factors, thought good, beſides the three for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <note place="margin">Foure ſhips laden.</note> ſhips that came firſt, to lade one other, to wit, the greater pinnaſſe called Friſland, whereof was Maſter <hi>Iacob Corneliſon,</hi> and Factor <hi>Walter Wille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens.</hi> Theſe foure ſhippes hauing receiued their ful fraight, and giuen notice on land of their departure (to the end that none of their creditours might bee vnpaid) and alſo hauing well prouided themſelues of rice and water, departed the thirteenth of Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:24997:8"/>
1599. and ſayled to Sumatra, where they tooke <note place="margin">Their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from Iaua the 13. of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary 1599.</note> in freſh water; for that the water of Bantam firſt waxeth white, and afterward crawleth full of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots.</p>
            <p>Upon the land of Sumatra we bartered kniues, ſpoones, looking-glaſſes, bels, needles and ſuch like, for ſundry fruits, to wit, melons, cucumbers, oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, garlike, and pepper though little in quantity, yet exceeding good.</p>
            <p>We had to deale with a notable Merchant of <note place="margin">Saſemolonke a notable mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant of Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</note> Bantam, named <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſemolonke,</hi> whoſe father was a Caſtilian, which ſold vs not much leſſe then an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth laſt of pepper<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He was moſt deſirous to haue traueiled with vs into Holland: but miſdoubting the diſpleaſure and euil will or the king, and fearing leaſt his goods might haue bin confiſcated, he durſt not aduenture vpon the voiage.</p>
            <p>Certaine daies before our departure from Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam were the other foure ſhippes diſpatched to go <note place="margin">The four other ſhips ſent to the Moluccas.</note> for the Moluccas, and ouer them was appointed as Admirall and Generall Maſter <hi>Wybrant van Warwicke</hi> in the ſhippe called Amſterdam, &amp; <hi>Iacob Heemskerck</hi> Viceadmirall in the ſhippe Gelderland, the other two ſhippes in conſort with them being Zeland and Vtrecht before mentioned</p>
            <p>Theſe foure made ſaile towards the Moluccas, and parted from vs the 8. of Ianuary in the night, and in taking of our leaues both of vs together, made ſuch a terrible thundering noiſe with our or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, that the townſemen were vp in Alarme, vntill they knewe the reaſon thereof. The people were glad of their departure, hauing ſome miſtruſt of vs, remaining there ſo ſtrong with 8. ſhips. And they aſked daily when wee ſhould depart, making great ſpeed to help vs vnto our lading, and ſhewing themſelues moſt ſeruiceable vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:24997:8"/>
The 11 of Ianuary 1599. we in the foure ſhippes laden with pepper departed from Bantam home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. The 13 we arriued at Sumatra. The 19 we ſhaped our courſe directly for Holland. The 3 of April we had ſight of <hi>Capo de buona eſperanza.</hi> The 8 of Aprill we doubled the ſaid Cape, proceeding on for the Iſle of Saint Helena, whither we came the twenty ſixt of the ſame moneth, and there refreſhed our ſelues for the ſpace of eight daies.</p>
            <p>In this Iſland we found a church with certaine boothes or tents in it, and the image of Saint He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena, as likewiſe a holy water-fat, and a ſprinkle to caſt or ſprinkle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy water: but we left all things in as good order as we found them.</p>
            <p>More ouer here we left behinde vs ſome remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances in writing, in token of our being there. At this place died of the bloudy flixe, the Pilot of our Admirall <hi>Kees Collen</hi> of Munickendam, a worthy man, to our great griefe.</p>
            <p>This Iſland (as <hi>Iohn Huighen van Linſchotten</hi> deſcribeth it) is repleniſhed with manifold commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, as namely with goates, wilde ſwine, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kies, partriges, pidgeons, &amp;c. But by reaſon that thoſe which arriue there vſe to diſcharge their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and to hunt and purſue the ſaide beaſtes and fowles, they are now growen exceeding wilde and hard to be come by. Certaine goates whereat we ſhotte fled vp to the high cliffes, ſo that it was impoſſible to get them. Likewiſe fiſhes wee could not catch ſo many as wee needed; but wee tooke in freſh water enough to ſerue vs till our arriuall in Holland.</p>
            <p>Here we left on land as a man baniſhed out of our <note place="margin">A man left on land at Saint Helena.</note> ſociety, one <hi>Peter Gisbrecht</hi> the maſters mate of the great pinnaſſe, becauſe hee had ſtroken the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:24997:9"/>
Very penitent hee was and ſorie for his miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meauour, and all of vs did our beſt endeuour to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his pardon: but (the orders &amp; ordinances wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eunto our whole company was ſworne being read before vs) we were conſtrained to ſurceaſe our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate ſuit, and he for the example of others to vndergo the ſeuere doome that was allotted him.</p>
            <p>There was deliuered vnto him a certaine quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of bread, oile, and rice, with hookes and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to fiſh withall, as alſo a hand gun and gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poulder.</p>
            <p>Hereupon we bad him generally farewell, beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching God to keepe and preſerue him from miſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and hoping that at ſome one time or other he ſhould finde deliuerance; for that all ſhippes ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to the Weſt Indies muſt there of neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh themſelues.</p>
            <p>Not far from this place we deſcried a ſaile which wee iudged to be ſome Frenchman, by whom per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture the ſaide baniſhed party might bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered.</p>
            <p>The fourth of May we ſet ſaile from Saint He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena, <note place="margin">The Iſle of Aſcenſion.</note> and the tenth of the ſame moneth wee paſſed by the Iſle of Aſcenſion. The 17 day wee paſſed the line. The 21 we ſawe the Pole-ſtarre. The 10 and 11 of Iune we had ſight of the Canaries. About the Azores wee ſtood in feare to meete with ſome ſpaniſh Armada, becauſe our men were growen faint and feeble by reaſon of their long voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. The 27 of Iune we entered the Spaniſh ſea. The 29 we found our ſelues to be in fortie foure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of northerly latitude. The 6 of Iuly our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mauritius had two of his maſtes blowne ouerboord; for which cauſe we were conſtrained to towe him along. The 11 of Iuly wee paſſed the Sorlings. The 13 we ſayled by Falmouth, Dart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:24997:9"/>
and the Quaſquets. The 17 we paſſed by Douer. The 19 meeting with ſome ſtormes and rainy weather we arriued at Texell in our owne natiue countrey, without any great miſfortune, ſaue that the Mauritius once ſtroke on ground.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing attained to our wiſhed home, we gaue God thankes for this our ſo happy and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous voiage: becauſe there neuer arriued in Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land any ſhippes ſo richly laden.</p>
            <p>Of pepper we brought eight hundreth tunnes, of <note place="margin">The particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of their rich lading.</note> Cloues two hundreth, beſides great quantity of Mace, Nutmegs, Cinamom, and other principall commodities. To conclude, this voiage was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in one yeare, two monethes and nineteene daies.</p>
            <p>We were ſailing outward from Texell to Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ſeuen moneths, we remained there ſixe weekes to take in our lading, and in ſix moneths we retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from Bantam in Iaua to Holland.</p>
            <p>The performance of this long and daungerous voiage in ſo ſhort time we aſcribed to Gods deuine &amp; wonderfull prouidence, hauing ſailed at the leaſt 8000. leagues, that is to ſay, twenty four thouſand Engliſh miles.</p>
            <p>The ioye of the ſafe arriuall of theſe ſhippes in Holland was exceeding great: and poſtes were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched to euery principall towne and citty to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh theſe acceptable newes.</p>
            <p>The merchants that were owners of theſe ſhips went ſtraight toward Texell for the refreſhing of their men, and for other neceſſary conſiderations, The Commiſſary or factor maſter <hi>Cornelis Heemſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerck</hi> together with <hi>Cornelis Knick,</hi> hied them with all ſpeed towardes the Eſtates generall and prince <hi>Mauritz</hi> his excellency, not onely to carry the ſaide good newes, but withal to preſent the letters of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:24997:10"/>
King of Iaua importing mutuall alliance, friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <note place="margin">Friendly let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents from the king of Iaua.</note> and free intercourſe of traffike in conſideration of their honourable, liberal, and iuſt dealings: they brought gifts alſo from the ſaid king of great price and value.</p>
            <p>The 27 of Iuly the Mauritius our Admirall to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Hollandia came before Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam: where they were ioyfully ſaluted with the ſound of eight trumpets, with banqueting, with ringing of bels, and with peales of ordinance, the Generall and other men of command being honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably receiued and welcommed by the citty.</p>
            <p>The merchants that aduentured in theſe voyages <note place="margin">A new ſupply of foure Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh ſhips ſent this laſt ſpring 1599. to the Eaſt Indies.</note> being in number ſixeteene or ſeauenteene (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the foure ſhippes gone from Iaua to the Moluccas, as is before mentioned) haue ſent this laſt ſpring 1599. foure ſhips more to continue this their traffique ſo happely begun: intending more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer the next ſpring to ſend a newe ſupply of other ſhips. And diuers other Marchants are likewiſe <note place="margin">An intent of the marchants of Amſterdam to ſend more ſhips the next ſpring 1600.</note> determined to enter into the ſame action.</p>
            <p>Of them that departed from Zeland theſe bring no newes, otherwiſe then is aforeſaide. Neither doe they report any thing of the two fleetes or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, that went from Roterdam the laſt ſommer 1598. ſhaping their courſe for the ſtreites of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellan</p>
            <p>Wee haue before made mention of an Indian called <hi>Abdoll,</hi> which was brought from Bantamin the firſt voiage, and had continued an whole win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or ſome eight monethes at Amſterdam in Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>Where during that ſpace (being a man of good ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation and experience, and borne about Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na) hee was well entreated, cheriſhed, and much made of.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:24997:10"/>
This <hi>Abdoll</hi> vpon his returne to Iaua being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <note place="margin">The relation of Abdoll an Indian, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Netherlands.</note> concerning the ſtate of the Netherlands, made vnto the principall men of Bantam a full de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration thereof, with all the rarities and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities which he had there ſeene and obſerued.</p>
            <p>Which albeit to the greateſt part of readers, who haue trauailed thoſe countries may ſeeme nothing ſtrange, and ſcarce worthy the relation: yet becauſe the report was made by ſo meere a ſtranger, &amp; with the Iauans that heard it wrought ſo good effect, I thought it not altogether impertinent here in this place to make rehearſall thereof.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore he tolde them (to their great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration in that hoat climate) That hee had ſeene aboue a thouſand ſleds drawen, and great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of horſemen riding vpon the frozen water in winter time, and that he had beheld more then two hundreth thouſand people trauailing on foote and on horſeback vpon the yce, as likewiſe that the ſaid ſleds were by horſes drawen ſo ſwiftly, that they made more way in three houres than any man could go on foote in tenne. And alſo that himſelfe for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure had been ſo drawen, the horſes being brauely adorned with bels and cymbals.</p>
            <p>Howbeit they would hardly be induced to beleeue that thoſe countries ſhould be ſo extreamely colde, and the waters ſo mightely frozen, as to beare ſuch an huge waight.</p>
            <p>Hee tolde them moreouer, that Holland was a free countrey, and that euery man there was his owne Maſter, and that there was not one ſlaue or captiue in the whole land.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, that the houſes, in regarde of their beautifull and lofty building, reſembled ſtately pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces, their inward rich furniture being altogether anſwerable to their outward glorious ſhew.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:24997:11"/>
Alſo, that the Churches (which he called <hi>Meſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas)</hi> were of ſuch bigneſſe &amp; capacity, as they might receiue the people of any prety towne.</p>
            <p>He affirmed likewiſe, that the Hollanders with the aſſiſtance of their confederates and friendes, maintained warres againſt the King of Spaine, whoſe mighty puiſſance is feared and redoubted of all the potentates of Europa.</p>
            <p>And albeit the ſaid warres had continued aboue thirty yeares, yet that during all that time the ſaide Hollanders increaſed both in might &amp; wealth.</p>
            <p>In like ſort he informed them of the ſtrange ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Holland, as being a countrey driuing vpon the water, the earth or ground whereof, they vſe inſteed of fewell, and that he had oft times warmed himſelfe, and had ſeene meat dreſſed with fires made of the ſame earth.</p>
            <p>In briefe, that it was a wateriſh and fenny coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and full of riuers, chanels, and ditches, and that therein was an innume<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able multitude of boates and ſmall ſhippes, as likewiſe great ſtore of tall and ſeruiceable ſhips, wherwith they ſailed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all quarters of the world, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This man <hi>Abdoll</hi> wee found to bee a captiue or ſlaue, and ſawe there his wife and children in very poore eſtate dwelling in a little cottage not ſo bigge as an hogſty: but by oure meanes he was made free and well rewarded.</p>
            <p>Not withſtanding he did but euil recompence vs: for he was charged to be the cauſe why pepper was ſolde dearer then ordinary vnto vs by a penny in the pounde: for hee told them that certaine ſhippes of Zeland and of other places were comming thither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes.</p>
            <p>And here the reader is to vnderſtand, that ſome foure moneths before the ſaid three ſhips arriued at
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:24997:11"/>
Bantam, the Portugales came with an Armada <note place="margin">The Portugals go about to hinder the trade of the Hollanders.</note> of gallies and fuſtes, being ſet foorth by the Viceroy of Goa and the gouernour of Molucca, to intercept the traffique of the Hollanders vnto thoſe partes, and to make them looſe all their expenſes, labour, and time which they had beſtowed: and alſo that their great and rich preſentes which they gaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Iauans the yeare before, to bring them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vtter deteſtation of the Hollanders, might not be altogether in vaine.</p>
            <p>The Generall of them that came from Goa was <hi>Don Luis,</hi> and of thoſe that came from Molucca <hi>Don Emanuell:</hi> who brought their Armada before Bantam, intending to ſurprize the citty, vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that the ſame preparation was made to reſiſt certaine pirates that came thither out of Holland the laſt yeare, and were determined this yeare alſo to come againe. Vnder theſe colours they ſought to take the towne and to fortifie the ſame, &amp; they built certaine ſconces in the countrey, committing great outrages, rauiſhing the Women, with many other villanies. Hereupon the townſemen of Bantam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſecretly prouided certaine gallies and fuſtes in great haſt, and ſodainly aſſailed the Portugales before they were well aware of them: for which cauſe finding but ſmall reſiſtance, they tooke 3 Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugale gallies with certaine ſhippes, and ſlewe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <note place="margin">The Portugals vanquiſhed.</note> 300 of them, taking 150 Portugales priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, of which we daily ſaw ſome going vp &amp; downe the ſtreetes of Bantam like ſlaues and captiues. Beſides theſe they tooke about 900 galli-ſlaues pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners.</p>
            <p>Vpon this hard ſucceſſe the reſt of the Portugals betooke themſelues to flight: but whither they bee arriued at Goa or Molucca, or what is become of them ſince, we are not able to auouch. The foreſaid
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:24997:12"/>
attempt and ouerthrowe, bred greater enmity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Portugales and them of Bantam, and gaue an eſpeciall occaſion for the aduauncement of our traffique.</p>
            <p>The fiue ſhips (whereof we haue before ſignified <note place="margin">The courſe which the fiue ſhips tooke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they were ſeparated from their three conſorts about the Cape of buona eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranza.</note> that foure were diſpatched by the whole companie for the Moluccas) being ſeuered beyonde the Cape of <hi>buona ſperanza</hi> from the other three of their company, and hauing quite loſt them, came all of them ſhortly after vnder an Iſland called (as it is thought) by the Portugals <hi>Iſola de Don Galopes:</hi> but they named it the Iſland of Mauritius. Here they entered into an hauen, calling the ſame <hi>Warwicke,</hi> after the name of their Viceadmirall, wherin they found very good harborow in twenty degrees of ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly latitude.</p>
            <p>This Iſland being ſituate to the Eaſt of Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſcar, <note place="margin">The Iſle of Mauritius de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</note> and containing as much in compaſſe as all Holland, is a very high, goodly, and pleaſant land, full of green &amp; fruitfull vallies, and repleniſhed with Palmito-trees, from the which droppeth holeſome wine. Likewiſe here are very many trees of right <note place="margin">Great ſtore of Ebenwood.</note> Ebenwood as black asiet, and as ſmooth &amp; hard as the very Iuory: and the quantity of this wood is ſo exceeding, that many ſhips may be laden herewith.</p>
            <p>For to ſaile into this hauen you muſt bring the two higheſt mountaines one ouer the other, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſixe ſmall Iſlands on your right hand, and ſo you may enter in vpon 30 fadomes of water. Lying win the bay, they had 10. 12. &amp; 14. fadoms. On their left ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was a litle Iſland which they named <hi>Hemſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerk</hi> Iſland, and the bay it ſelfe they called <hi>Warwick</hi> bay, as is before mentioned. Here they tarried 12 daies to refreſh themſelues, finding in this place great quantity of foules twiſe as bigge as ſwans, which they called Walghſtocks or Wallowbirdes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:24997:12"/>
being very good meat. But finding alſo aboundance of piogeons &amp; popiniayes, they diſdained any more to eat of thoſe great foules, calling them (as before) Wallowbirds, that is to ſay, lothſome or fulſome birdes.</p>
            <p>Of the ſaide Pidgeons and Popiniayes they found great plenty being very fat and good meate, which they could eaſily take and kil euen with little ſtickes: ſo tame they are by reaſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Iſle is not inhabited, neither be the liuing creatures therein accuſtomed to the ſight of men.</p>
            <p>Here they found rauens alſo, and ſuch abundance of fiſh, that two men were able to catch enough for all fiue ſhips.</p>
            <p>Tortoiſes they founde ſo huge, that tenne men <note place="margin">Huge Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toiſes.</note> might ſit and dine in one of their ſhelles, and one of them would creepe away, while two men ſtood vpon the backe thereof.</p>
            <p>Here was founde waxe alſo whiter then any of ours, lying about the ſtrande, bleached (as it is like) by the ſunne: and in ſome of this waxe there were Arabian letters or characters printed: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is probable, that ſome Arabian ſhip might bee caſt away thereabout, out of which the ſaid waxe might be driuen on land.</p>
            <p>They found like wiſe Corall on this land, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">Corall.</note> trees which we call Palmitos, whereout drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth <note place="margin">Palmitos.</note> wine as out of the Coco-tree: which wine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kept, hath his operation as our new preſt wine, but after ſome time it commeth vnto the tul vertue and perfection.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Palmitos they eſteemed to bee a kinde of wilde date-trees.</p>
            <p>We ſought all the Iſland ouer for men, but could find none, for that it was wholly deſtitute of Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:24997:13"/>
Vpon this Iſland we built an houſe with a pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit therein, and left behind vs certaine writings as a token and remembrance of our being there, and vpon the pulpit we left a Bible and a pſalter lying.</p>
            <p>Thus after 12 daies aboad at this Iſland, being well refreſhed, they tooke in excellent freſh water be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">A good wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring place.</note> eaſie to get, and very ſweet and ſauory to drinke, and then ſet ſaile, meeting the three other ſhips their conſorts at the time and place before mentioned.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:24997:13"/>
            <head>A briefe deſcription of the voiage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>fore handled, in manner of a Iournall.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="May" type="month">
               <head>MAIE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE firſt of Maie 1598. with the eight ſhippes before mentioned, we ſet ſaile in the name of God from <hi>Texell</hi> in <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third of May we paſſed along the coaſt of <hi>England,</hi> deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crying ſome of her Maieſties ſhips, and they vs, whom we honoured with diſcharge of our artillery.</p>
               <p>The fourteenth, we had ſight of the Iſle of <hi>Porto Santo</hi> lying in thirty two degrees.</p>
               <p>The sixteenth, wee came within ſight of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The twenty two, we firſt ſaw flying fiſhes.</p>
               <p>The twenty three, we paſſed by the Iſle <hi>Dell Sall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The thirty one, we had a great ſtorme, ſo that we loſt ſight one of another: but by night we came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="June" type="month">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:24997:14"/>
               <head>IVNE.</head>
               <p>The eighth of Iune wee croſſed the <hi>Equinoctiall</hi> line.</p>
               <p>The twenty foure wee ſayled by the ſholdes of <hi>Braſile</hi> lying vnder eighteene degrees of Southerly Latitude.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="July" type="month">
               <head>IVLIE.</head>
               <p>The twenty one of Iuly we got to the height of the <hi>Cape</hi> of <hi>buona eſperanza.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the thirtith of Iuly till the ſecond of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, we continually ſayled in ſight of the land of the foreſaid <hi>Cape.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="August" type="month">
               <head>AVGVST.</head>
               <p>The ſeuenth and eighth of Auguſt wee had ſuch foule and ſtormy weather, that fiue ſhips of our company were ſeparated from vs, whom we ſaw no more vntill they came to vs before <hi>Bantam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Twenty ſixt we deſcryed the Iſland of <hi>Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſcar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The twenty nine came by vs the ſhip called the <hi>Long barke</hi> of <hi>Zeland,</hi> hauing in her but nine ſound men, tenne dead, and the reſt all ſicke: but the ſame night we loſt the ſight of her againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="September" type="month">
               <head>SEPTEMBER.</head>
               <p>The ſeauenth of September, we came before the Iſland of <hi>Santa Maria,</hi> and afterward wee put into the great bay of <hi>Antogill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſixteenth of September, wee ſet ſaile from thence, directing our courſe for <hi>Iaua.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="October" type="month">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:24997:14"/>
               <head>OCTOBER.</head>
               <p>The firſt of October, wee got to the heighth of <hi>Bantam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fifteenth, died the firſt man in our <hi>Admirall.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="November" type="month">
               <head>NOVEMBER.</head>
               <p>THe nineteenth of Nouember, we came within ſight of <hi>Sumatra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The twenty ninth, wee road before the citty of <hi>Bantam:</hi> And the thirtith, we payed our toll to the gouernour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="January" type="month">
               <head>IANVARIE.</head>
               <p>ANd vpon Newyeares date 1599. <hi>Stilo Nouo,</hi> we began to take in ourlading.</p>
               <p>Then came vnto vs before <hi>Bantam,</hi> with great idie and triumph, our fiue ſeparated ſhippes, all the people ſtanding vpon the ſhore gazing, and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting ſome harme intended againſt them.</p>
               <p>The eighth of Ianuary, foure of the ſaid 5 new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſhippes (God ſend them a proſperous voyage) ſet ſaile toward the <hi>Moluccas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer our foure ſhippes being well and rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laden at <hi>Bantam</hi> made ſaile homewarde the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth of Ianuary, and the thirteenth, wee were ſhot as farre as the Iſles of <hi>Sumatra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The nineteenth, we proceeded thence on our voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and the ſame day, to the great griefe of vs all, died the Pilot of our <hi>Admirall.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="April" type="month">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:24997:15"/>
               <head>APRILL.</head>
               <p>THe third of Aprill, we deſcried the land of <hi>Capo de buona eſperanza.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The eighth, wee doubled the ſame <hi>Cape,</hi> thence ſhaping our courſe for the Iſland of Saint <hi>Helena,</hi> where the twenty sixt we happily arriued, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from thence vpon the fourth of Maie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="May" type="month">
               <head>MAIE.</head>
               <p>THe tenth of Maie, wee ſailed by the Iſle of <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſeauenteenth, we paſſed the <hi>Equinoctiall line.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The twenty one, we ſaw the <hi>North ſtarre.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="June" type="month">
               <head>IVNE.</head>
               <p>THe ninth and tenth of Iune, we had ſight of the <hi>Canaries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The twenty ſeauen, wee ſayled vpon the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Sea.</p>
               <p>The twenty nine, we were in fortie four degrees.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="July" type="month">
               <head>IVLIE.</head>
               <p>THe fourth of Iuly, we ſaw behind vs two ſailes, one before the other, which were the firſt that we had ſeene of a long time.</p>
               <p>The ſixt of Iuly our <hi>Admirall</hi> had both his Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſt and Maine-maſt blowne ouer boord.</p>
               <p>The eleuenth, we paſſed the <hi>Sorlings,</hi> the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, <hi>Falmouth, Plimmouth,</hi> and the <hi>Quaſquets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſeauenteenth, we came before <hi>Douer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:24997:15"/>
The nineteenth, wee had foule and ſtormy wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, at what time by Gods good bleſſing wee arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in our natiue countrey at <hi>Texell</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing performed in the ſhort ſpace of one yeare, two moneths and nineteene daies, almoſt as long a voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, as if we ſhould haue compaſſed the globe of the earth, and bringing home with vs our full ſtraight of rich and gainfull Marchandize.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
